<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A commission to the Right Honourable Richard Lord Viscount Ranelagh and others to be commissioners for the manageing of His Majesties Treasury and revenue in Ireland.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2940A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231303</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899851</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">136971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 136971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2457:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A commission to the Right Honourable Richard Lord Viscount Ranelagh and others to be commissioners for the manageing of His Majesties Treasury and revenue in Ireland.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Newcomb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In the Savoy [London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ranelagh, Richard Jones, --  Earl of, 1638?-1712 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Treasury --  Administration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:136971:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:136971:1"/>
            <p>A COMMISSION To the Right Honourable <hi>RICHARD</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>RANELAGH</hi> AND OTHERS, To be Commiſsioners FOR THE MANAGEING OF His Majeſties TREASURY and REVENUE IN IRELAND.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Newcomb,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commission">
            <pb facs="tcp:136971:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:136971:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms of Charles II</figDesc>
               </figure> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>II.</hi> directs this Commiſſion to <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Rane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagh,</hi> and eight other principal Commiſſioners; and in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective abſence to nine others.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES</hi> the Second, by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To Our Right Truſty, and Right Welbeloved Couſin,
<hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh;</hi> Our Truſty and Welbeloved, Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> and Sir <hi>James Hayes,</hi> Knights; <hi>John Bence, George Daſhwod, Joſeph Dean, Robert Huntingdon, John Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kingdon,</hi> Eſquires; and in the abſence of the ſaid Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved
<hi>Robert Sands</hi> Eſquire, and in the abſence of the ſaid Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Tayler</hi> Eſquire; and in the abſence of the ſaid Sir <hi>James Hayes,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>John Hayes</hi> Eſquire; and in the abſence of the ſaid <hi>John Bence,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>Thomas Scarth</hi> Merchant; and in the abſence of the ſaid <hi>George Daſhwood,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>Edward Roberts</hi> Eſquire; and in the abſence of the ſaid
<hi>Joſeph Dean,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>Joſeph Dean</hi> the younger Gentleman; and in the abſence of the ſaid <hi>Robert Huntingdon,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>Griffith Bodurda</hi> Eſquire; and in the abſence of the ſaid <hi>John Stepney,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>Lancelot Stepney</hi> Gentleman; and in the abſence of the ſaid <hi>Richard Kingdon,</hi> to Our Truſty and Welbeloved <hi>John Winkworth</hi> Eſquire;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:136971:3"/>Greeting.<note place="margin">Recital of a Grant (to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> Lord Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> and eight others, of all His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Revenue in
<hi>Ireland</hi>) Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Auguſt 4. 1673.</hi>
               </note> WHEREAS, by an Indenture, bearing date the fourth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt paſt, before the date of theſe preſents, and made between Our Self of the one part, and you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount
<hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence, George Daſhwood, Joſeph Dean, Robert Huntingdon, John Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kingdon</hi> of the other part; We were Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed amongſt other things, to Covenant, Grant, and Agree to and with you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſc. <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Hayes, Iohn Bence, George Daſhwood, Joſeph Dean, Robert Huntingdon, John Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Rich. Kingdon,</hi> and every of you, you and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of your Heirs, Executors and Adminiſtrators, that there ſhould be from time to time, during the term in the ſaid Indenture mentioned, ſuch and ſo many Commiſsions iſſued out under Our Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount
<hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence, George Daſhwood, Joſeph Dean, Robert Huntingdon, John Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kingdon;</hi> the ſurvivors, or ſurvivor of you; or the Executors, or Adminiſtrators of the ſurvivor of you, or ſuch other diſcreet, able, and fit Perſons, as you ſhall humbly deſire (which Commiſsions ſo to be iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, ſhould ſufficiently authorize and impower the Perſons therein to be named, to act as our Officers) as ſhould be found neceſſary to be done in the managing of, and for the better and more ſpeedy Levying, Collecting, Sueing for, Recovering and Receiving, or otherwiſe Compounding for, and Diſcharging of all and every our Rents, Revenues, Profits, Duties, Incomes, certain and caſual, ordinary and extraordinary whatſoever, in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> (not remitted or pardoned, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe before the Five and twentieth day of <hi>December</hi> then laſt paſt, granted away and diſpoſed) as well ſuch, as upon, or before the Five and twentieth day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> then laſt paſt, were in arrear, and were then unpaid, as ſuch as from and after the ſaid time, until the ſix and twentieth day of <hi>December,</hi> which ſhould be in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:136971:3"/>year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſeventy and five, were, or ſhould be, by any matter of Record or otherwiſe howſoever, due, owing, or payable to us, or which might, or ought to have been, or may, before the ſaid Six and twentieth day of
<hi>December,</hi> in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſeventy and five, be Taxed, Levied, Collected, Recovered, Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, paid or payable to us, our Heirs or Succeſſors, out of or for any Lands, Tenements, or Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or all or any the Eſtates Real or Perſonal, of any Perſon or Perſons, Bodies Politique or Corporate, or otherwiſe, by reaſon of any Tax, Aſſeſsment, Subſidy, Impoſitions, Contract, Covenant, Agreement, Accompt, Debt, Duty, ſum or ſums of Money, matter or thing impoſed or made, or iſſued, or which did or ſhould ariſe, or grow due within the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> before the ſaid ſix and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>December,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix hundred ſeventy and five, including the Rents, Duties, and Payments, which ſhould be due for the time incurred before the ſaid ſix and twentieth day of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred ſeventy and five, though the ſame may be payable, or Inſtalments made, or time given for the payment thereof, after that day; and that all and every the ſums of Money then due, or which at any time after the date of the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, and before the ſix and twentieth day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix hundred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty five, ſhould grow due or payable to us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, whether for Rent reſerved upon the Farm of the great Branches of Our Revenue in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> or for Arrears, or otherwiſe howſoever, ſhould from time to time during the term in the ſaid Indenture mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, anſwered, and brought into Our Receipt of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer at
<hi>Dublin,</hi> in ſuch manner as the ſame had been before that time uſed to be paid, and would and ought to have been paid, if the ſaid Indenture had not been made, to the end, that our Treaſure ſo brought in,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:136971:4"/>and remaining in Our Exchequer there, might from time to time he iſſued out from thence, and applyed to ſuch Uſes, Intents and Purpoſes, as in the ſaid Indenture are mentioned, and thereby are undertaken to be done and performed; and that for the better effecting thereof, and more orderly and legal proceeding therein, We would forthwith in due form of Law, Conſtitute, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize, Commiſsionate and Appoint, the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount
<hi>Ranelagh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His Majeſty by the ſaid Grant, did covenant to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>at the ſaid <hi>Rich.</hi> Lord Viſc.
<hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Alex. Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence,</hi> and <hi>George Daſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> to Receive and Iſſue His Majeſties Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue.</note> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence,</hi> and <hi>George Daſhwood,</hi> to be our Officers or Commiſsioners, and to have the ſole care and cuſtody of all Moneys ſo brought in, and the ſole power to receive the ſaid Moneys from time to time, and give Acquittances and Diſcharges for the ſame, and to iſſue out the ſaid Moneys, and pay the ſame to the ends and uſes in the ſaid Indenture menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, with ſuch Clauſes to be inſerted in ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion as may be ſufficient totally to prohibit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain any other Perſon or Perſons, from acting, or any way intermedling therein, upon any other pretence of authority whatſoever, during the continuance of the ſaid Undertaking in the ſaid Indenture mentioned.</p>
            <p>AND We were further Graciouſly pleaſed, by the ſaid Indenture, to Covenant and Agree, to and with you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence,</hi> and <hi>George Daſhwood,</hi> that all Orders, Warrants, Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Commands, which at any time after the date of the ſaid Indenture, and before the ſix and twentieth day of <hi>December,</hi> in the year of our Lord One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred ſeventy and five, ſhould be made and ſigned, touching or concerning the iſſuing out of any moneys for paying any part of Our ſaid Revenue, ſhould be ſo made and ſigned by the Lord Lieutenant or other chief Governor or Governors of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, and be directed to you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence,</hi> and <hi>George Daſhwood</hi> onely, to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:136971:4"/>intent that you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſc. <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir
<hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence,</hi> and <hi>George Daſhwood,</hi> might wholly apply the ſaid Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys to the uſes and intents of the ſaid Indenture, and to the execution and performance of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking in the ſaid Indenture mentioned, as in and by the ſaid Indenture, amongſt divers other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, Clauſes, and Agreements therein contained, may more plainly appear.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh</hi> and his Partners have humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to appoint all the ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> artners, and in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective abſence, nine other perſons to be Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue.</note>AND, whereas you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir
<hi>James Hayes, John Bence, George Daſhwood, Joſeph Dean, Robert Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, John Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kingdon,</hi> have ſince humbly beſought us, that you the ſaid
<hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> and in your abſence the ſaid <hi>Robert Sands,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> and in your abſence the ſaid <hi>Thomas Tayler,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes,</hi> and in your abſence the ſaid <hi>John Hayes, Iohn Bence,</hi> and in your abſence the ſaid <hi>Thomas Scarth, George Daſhwood,</hi> and in your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence the ſaid <hi>Edward Roberts, Ioſeph Dean,</hi> and in your abſence the ſaid <hi>Ioſeph Dean</hi> the younger, <hi>Robert Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingdon,</hi> and in your abſence the ſaid <hi>Griffith Bodurda, Iohn Stepney,</hi> and in your abſence the ſaid <hi>Lancelott Stepney,</hi> and
<hi>Richard Kingdon,</hi> and in your abſence, the ſaid <hi>Iohn Winkworth,</hi> ſhould have all and every the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Authorities by us Covenanted in and by the ſaid Indenture, to be by us granted unto you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir
<hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence,</hi> and <hi>George Daſhwood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Body of the Commiſsion whereby all the nine Partners, and nine others in their reſpective abſence are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</note>NOW therefore Know ye, That We repoſing eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Truſt and Confidence in your Abilities, Fidelity, and prudent Circumſpection, HAVE Nominated, Conſtituted and Appointed, and by theſe Preſents do Nominate, Conſtitute, and Appoint you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount
<hi>Ranelagh,</hi> and in your abſence, you the ſaid <hi>Robert Sands,</hi> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence;</hi> and in your abſence, you the ſaid <hi>Thomas Tayler,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes;</hi> and in your abſence, you the ſaid <hi>John Hayes, John
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:136971:5"/>Bence;</hi> and in your abſence you the ſaid <hi>Thomas Scarth, George Daſhwood;</hi> and in your abſence you the ſaid <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Roberts, Joſeph Dean;</hi> and in your abſence, you the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Dean</hi> the younger, <hi>Robert Huntingdon;</hi> and in your abſence, you the ſaid <hi>Griffith Bodurda, John Stepney;</hi> and in your abſence, you the ſaid <hi>Lancelot Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kingdon;</hi> and in your abſence, you the ſaid <hi>John Winkworth,</hi> to be Our Commiſsioners accordingly:<note place="margin">Power given to the Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and every of them or theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by them, to view, ſearch, examine, and take Copies of any Records or Writings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the premiſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fee for the ſame.</note> GIVING, and by theſe Preſents Grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto you, and every of you, and to all and every other Perſon and. Perſons imployed by you, or any of you, full power and authority, at all convenient times, and in orderly manner, to view, inſpect, ſearch and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, all Rolls, Records, Books, Accompts, Papers, and other Memorials whatſoever, remaining in Our Courts of Exchequer, or in any other Our Courts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, or in the Clerks of our reſpective Councils cuſtody, or in any other place, or in the hands of any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon belonging to us within Our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> or Our ſaid Kingdom of
<hi>Ireland,</hi> touching or concerning the premiſſes, and which may any ways conduce to the finding out of all ſuch Rents, and other the Premiſes, as ſhall be due, owing, and unpaid, as aforeſaid, and to take Copies of the ſame or any of them, the ſaid Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies to be made by the reſpective Officers or Perſons in whoſe cuſtody the ſame do or ſhall remain, or by their Clerks or Servants, without any Fee, or other charge to be paid for the ſame.<note place="margin">Power to five or more of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to meet and call before them ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as they ſhall judge requiſite for the diſcovery and recovering of the premiſſes, and any Writing or evidence belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty concerning the ſame, and to examine him or them touching the ſame.</note> AND further, We do hereby Give and Grant unto you Our ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners hereby appointed, or any five or more of you, ſuch convenient times and places as you ſhall think fit and appoint, full power and authority to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and to call before you all or any ſuch Perſon or Perſons, as you ſhall judge requiſite or neceſſary, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to, or concerning the diſcovery and finding out and recovering of the Premiſſes, or any of them, ſo due and unpaid as aforeſaid, and any Writing or Evidence belonging to Us concerning the ſame, and to examine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:136971:5"/>him, them, or any of them,<note place="margin">To enquire by the oaths of good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men, or by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawful means, as well by examining wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes upon oath, as otherwiſe, whereby the truth may be beſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</note> touching or concerning the ſame, and to enquire, and cauſe to be enquired by the Oaths of good and lawful Men, or by any other law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ways or means, by which the truth may be beſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and known, as well by examining Witneſſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath as otherwiſe. And if after ſuch ſearch and examination made, it ſhall happen, that any Perſon or Perſons who ſhall be found in Arrear,<note place="margin">If after ſearch or examination any perſon be found in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear, and indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by Law, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſubmit to, or give ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, by Inſtallments, to certify the ſame into the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and to cauſe them to be effectually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt according to Law.</note> and Indebted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Us in any ſum or ſums of Money, for any the Rents, Revenues, and Profits, or other the Premiſſes before mentioned, ſhall deſire to defend him or themſelves by Law againſt the Debts and Duties ſo found to be ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then and there demanded of him, rather then ſubmit to the payment thereof, or give ſecurity for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame by ſuch inſtalments as ſhall be offered to him or them; then, and in ſuch caſe, Our Will and Pleaſure is, that you forthwith Tranſmit and Certify the name or names of ſuch Perſon or Perſons not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to ſuch payment, or giving ſecurity as aforeſaid, into the Court of Our Exchequer at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and that you cauſe him or them to be effectually proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt according to Law: And to the end Our Will and Pleaſure may be the better performed and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and the Money ſo due and in Arrear, may the more ſpeedily and effectually be Recovered, Levied,<note place="margin">The chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and others whom it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, are in His Majeſties name, at the requeſt of the Commiſsion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to iſſue Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions Writs and Proceſſes (without any Fee) for recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and bringing in of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Revenue and Debts, according to the courſe of the Exchequer, wherein all His Majeſties Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are to be aiding and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> and paid as aforeſaid, OUR FURTHER Will and Pleaſure is, and We do hereby Authorize, Command, and Require Our Lord Lieutenant, Juſtices, or chief Governor or Governors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Our Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Barons of Our Court of Exchequer there, for the time being, and all others whom it ſhall or may concern, that they and every of them during the continuance of this Our Commiſsion in force, at the deſire and requeſt of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners or any of you, do award, make, and deliver unto you or any of you, without charge or Fee, all and every ſuch Commiſsion and Commiſsions of Enquiry, Writ
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:136971:6"/>and Writs, Proceſs and other proceedings whatſoever, in the name of Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors, as ſhall or may be neceſſary for the more ſpeedy recovery, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, and Levying of all and every Our ſaid Rents, Revenues, Profits, and other the Premiſſes, and are agreeable to, and may ſtand and conſiſt with the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent courſe and practice of Our ſaid Court of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, heretofore uſed for the recovery of Debts due and owing to Us, or any of Our Royal Progenitors or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, and that they and every of them, as alſo all Sheriffs, Bailiffs, and other Our inferior Officers and Miniſters in their ſeveral and reſpective places, be from time to time aiding and aſsiſting to you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, and every of you, in obeying ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, as from time to time ſhall be directed to them, and in the execution of the premiſſes as becometh. AND FURTHER, in purſuance of a Covent in that behalf, in the ſaid Indenture mentioned, and at the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid humble ſupplication of you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir
<hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence, George Daſhwood, Joſeph Dean, Robert Huntingdon, John Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kingdon,</hi> and of Our eſpecial Grace, certain Knowledge, and meer motion, in conſideration of the aſſured Truſt and Confidence we repoſe in you Our ſaid Commiſsioners hereby appointed,<note place="margin">Power to the Commiſsioners, or any five or more of them, whereof one to be always of each diviſion; the whole eighteen being divided in three diviſions, ſix in a diviſion, to execute and exerciſe the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Places of the Treaſurer, Receiver-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer at Wars, from the date hereof, until the <hi>26</hi> of <hi>December 1675.</hi>
               </note> We have Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Granted, and by theſe Preſents do Give and Grant to you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, and to any five or more of you, or which five or more of you We Will that of you the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Hayes, Iohn Bence, Robert Sands, John Hayes,</hi> or
<hi>Thomas Scarth,</hi> there ſhall be always one; and of which ſaid five or more of you, We al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Will, that of you the ſaid <hi>George Daſhwood, Robert Huntingdon, Richard Kingdon, Edward Roberts, Griffith Bodurda,</hi> or <hi>John Winkeworth,</hi> there ſhall be always one; AND of which five or more of you,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:136971:6"/>We likewiſe Will, that of you the ſaid Sir <hi>Alexander Bence, Joſeph Dean, John Stepney, Thomas Tayler, Joſeph Dean</hi> the younger, or <hi>Lancelot Stepney,</hi> there ſhall be always one full Power and Authority to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and execute the ſeveral Places and Offices of Vice-Treaſurer, and General-Receiver of all Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, Profits and Caſualties whatſoever, that be or ſhall be due to Us, Our Heirs or Succeſſors, from time to time within Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and alſo to exerciſe and execute the Office and Place of Treaſurer at Wars within Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the day of the date of theſe Preſents, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the twenty ſixth day of <hi>December,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of Our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty and five, by your ſelves, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, or by the ſufficient Deputy or Deputies of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or of any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, in as full and ample manner, to all intents and purpoſes as any Vice-Treaſurer, General-Receiver, and Treaſurer at Wars, have done or might do the ſame; AND where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſaid Lord Viſcount
<hi>Ranelagh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Clauſe in purſuance of a Covenant in the Indenture, dated the <hi>4</hi> of <hi>Auguſt (71)</hi> for payment of the Vice-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers Fees) for inabling the Commiſſioners to receive the Fees due to the Vice-Treaſurer, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver-general, and Treaſurer at Wars, for the ſaid uſe.</note> Sir <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hayes, John Bence, George Daſhwood, Joſeph Dean, Robert Huntingdon, John Stepney,</hi> and
<hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Kingdon,</hi> have Covenanted with Us, that you will pay unto the Vice-Treaſurer of
<hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, during the time or this your undertaking, all the Fees and Perquiſites, due unto and uſually received by the Vice-Treaſurer. NOW the better to enable you to pay to Our Vice-Treaſurer, General-Receiver, and Treaſurer at Wars of Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, all the ſaid Profits and Fees ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken by you to be paid, and all other Profits, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties and Fees, which Our Vice-Treaſurer, Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-General, and Treaſurer at Wars ought to have had for all or any Moneys which ſhall by you or any five or more of you, or your Deputy or Deputies be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:136971:7"/>payd during this your undertaking, or afterwards, by vertue of, or in purſuance of this your undertaking, if the ſame had been paid by Our Vice-Treaſurer, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral-Receiver, and Treaſurer at Wars, of Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, to the intent, and upon Truſt and Confidence, that you ſhall pay the ſame accordingly. We do further Will and Grant, that during the time aforeſaid, and until the ſaid twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſixth day of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred ſeventy and five, you Our ſaid Commiſsioners hereby appointed, or any ſuch five or more of you as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or the ſufficient Deputy or Deputies of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or of ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, Do and ſhall Demand, Take, Receive, and Have all and ſingular the Fees, Rights, Priviledges, Profits, Perquiſites, Commodities, Advantages, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties whatſoever; unto the ſaid Offices of Vice-Treaſurer, General-Receiver, and Treaſurer at Wars, every or any of them, by any ways or means, by Right belonging or appertaining, and in as large, ample, and beneficial manner, as any Vice-Treaſurer, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral-Receiver, or Treaſurer at Wars within Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> hath or ought to have, had, held, taken, perceived, received, uſed, or enjoyed, or unto the ſaid Places or Offices, every or any of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing or appertaining; AND We do alſo hereby, upon the Truſt aforeſaid, for Us, Our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, Grant that it ſhall and may be lawful to, and for you Our ſaid Commiſsioners hereby appointed, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, or to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty or Deputies of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or of any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, to demand take and receive of our loving Subjects, to whom you our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, or the Deputy or Deputies of you our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, ſhall deliver and pay any ſum or ſums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:136971:7"/>within Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by vertue or reaſon of the exerciſing or executing of the ſaid Place or Office of Vice-Treaſurer, and General-Receiver and Treaſurer at Wars, the Fee or Sum of Sixpence of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Engliſh</hi> Money, for every twenty ſhillings of like Money of <hi>England,</hi> that you Our ſaid Commiſsioners or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, or the Deputy or Deputies of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, ſhall pay to any of Our Subjects within Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in as large, free, and ample manner, as any Vice-Treaſurer, or General-Receiver of Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> hath Demanded, Received, and Taken the ſame;<note place="margin">Power to the Commiſsioners, or any five or more of them as aforeſaid, to have the cuſtody of, and to receive and give Acquittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, (whereof Entries are to be made with one of the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, or Clerk of the Pells) and to iſſue the ſame to the uſes of the ſaid Indenture.</note> AND We further Will and Grant, that you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, or the Deputy or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, have the ſole Care and Cuſtody of all Moneys to be paid and payable to Us in the ſaid Indenture mentioned, and the ſole pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to receive the ſaid Moneys from time to time, and to give Acquittances and Diſcharges for the ſame, which ſhall be as ſufficient diſcharges to the Subjects, paying the ſaid Moneys, as any Acquittances heretofore gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and commonly called <hi>Exchequer Acquittances,</hi> have, and ought to be, to all intents and purpoſes pleadable in Law and Equity, by all Our loving Subjects, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and producing the ſame, ſo as the ſame be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the uſual manner with one of the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains of Our ſaid Exchequer, and the Clerk of the Pells, and to iſſue out the ſaid Moneys, and pay the ſame,<note place="margin">The Lord <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gier,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to act or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle herein on any pretence whatſoever, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the ſaid Indenture.</note> to the ends and uſes in the ſaid Indenture men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; AND We do hereby ſtrictly prohibit and reſtrain <hi>Francis</hi> Lord
<hi>Angier,</hi> Our Vice-Treaſurer, General-Receiver, and Treaſurer at Wars in Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> his Deputy or Deputies, and all and every other Perſon and Perſons from acting, or any ways intermedling therein, upon any pretence of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:136971:8"/>Commiſsion or Commiſsions, or other Authority whatſoever, during the continuance of the ſaid under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking in the ſaid Indenture mentioned.<note place="margin">All Orders, Warrants, and Directions for the payment of any Money, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the ſaid Commiſsioners, to the end the ſame may be wholly applyed to the ends and uſes of the ſaid Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> AND WE do further Will and Declare Our Royal pleaſure to be, That all Orders, Warrants, Directions, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, which at any time after the date of the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, and before the ſaid ſix and twentieth day of <hi>December</hi> in the year of Our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſeventy and five, ſhall be made and Signed, touching or concerning the iſſuing out of any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys for paying any part of Our ſaid Revenue, ſhall be ſo Made and Signed by the Lord Lieutenant, or other chief Governor or Governors of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, and be directed unto you Our ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners hereby appointed, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, or the Deputy or Deputies of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, only to the intent that you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or the Deputy or Deputies of you Our ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, may wholly apply the ſaid Moneys, to the uſes and intents of the ſaid recited Indenture, and to the execution and performance of the undertaking therein mentioned. AND OUR FURTHER Will and Pleaſure is,<note place="margin">The Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners are directed within forty days after the end of every Quarter, to pay the Fees to the Vice-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer for the time being.</note> and We do hereby Will and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you Our ſaid Commiſsioners hereby appointed, or any ſuch five or more or you as aforeſaid, or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty or Deputies of you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, from time to time, during the continuance of the undertaking in the ſaid recited Indenture mentioned, quarterly, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in forty days after each quarter, well and truly to pay, or cauſe to be paid unto Our Vice-Treaſurer of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the time being, all and every the uſual and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed Fees and Profits, for, and in reſpect of any ſum or ſums of Money, by you Our ſaid Commiſsioners, or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, or by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:136971:8"/>the Deputy or Deputies of you Our ſaid Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners,<note place="margin">The Office of the Receipt, and the lower Rooms of the New Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom-houſe at <hi>Dublin,</hi> for the executing of this Commiſsion are granted to the Commiſsioners, and are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto them, Fitted and Repaired at His Majeſties charge. The Commiſſion under the Great Seal, bears date at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> in the
<hi>23</hi> year of His Majeſties Reign.</note> or any ſuch five or more of you as aforeſaid, to be iſſued and payd out as aforeſaid, as Our Vice-Treaſurer, General-Receiver, and Treaſurer at Wars for the time being, could, or ought to have received, if ſuch Warrants had been directed unto, or ſuch pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments had been made by him. AND for the more eaſe and convenience in the executing of this Our Commiſsion, We do hereby Allow and Grant unto you, not onely the uſe of the Office of the Receipt, but alſo of the lower Rooms of Our New Cuſtom-houſe at <hi>Dublin,</hi> which We hereby Require and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be forthwith delivered to you, and be Fitted and Repaired at Our proper Coſts and Charges.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>In witneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Witneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
